Abraham: There are many terms that we will
discuss throughout this course that are
used in cyber security and some of them
we hear more often than others let’s look
at some of the most common used terms.
Nicole: Threat -as we have already
discussed is the ability of hackers
or threat actors to target and
adversely impact organisational
systems, operations, and assets.
Threats take many different forms such as
malware, data breaches and DoS attacks.
Abraham: Vulnerabilities-refers
to any week spot within the cyber
security of an organisation that
allows anyone to enter their systems
and steal anything of value like data
that may compromise and adversely
impact an organisations operation.
Hackers use these in various ways
to gain access and attack a system.
Vulnerabilities are also
known as the attack surface.
Nicole: Software flaws are some of the
most common vulnerabilities such as,
bugs or backdoors which enable access
by bypassing normal security measures.
These may be as a result of a poor
system design processes or mistakes
made when the system was set up and
can go undetected for some time.
User error can make a system
vulnerable for example when the user
unwittingly clicks on a malicious
link in an email or text message.
They may also consistently use the
same obvious email for everything
easily guessed by the hacker.
Hackers can easily trick users into
giving away information by a variety
of different phishing attacks.
Abraham: When an attack happens on the
day a weakness is discovered in software
this is classed as a zero day attack.
This is because the hackers are
aware of the flaw and launch
their attack before the software
company can release the patch.
Nicole: Risk- refers to the level
of impact a cyber attack may have on
an organisation and its operations
for example financial loss,
disruption, and damage to reputation.
It usually involves a combination of
threat, vulnerability, and impact.
Organisations may face a greater
risk if they have more valuable
information or financial assets.
Add to that a flaw or a vulnerability
then the risk of attack would be high.
Malicious threat actors also
like to target companies and
organisations they don’t like so
as to damage their reputations.
Abraham: Exploits- are codes
that take advantage of a
software vulnerability or flaw.
They allow unauthorised access
remotely, gaining elevated privileges
or to move deeper into the network.
Exploit tools can also be embedded
into compromised webpages and as
the user navigates through them
the tool scans their device for
vulnerabilities and inserts the malware.
They can also be used as part
of a multi-component attack.